<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Newes out of Germanie. A most wonderfull and true discouse of a cruell murderer, who had kylled in his life tyme, nine hundred, threescore and odde persons among which six of them were his owne children begotten on a young woman which he forceablie kept in a caue seuen yeeres, with the manner how he was taken, and the aboundaunce of wealth that was found in the said caue: executed at Berkessell on the 14. of Iune. Translated and published according to the Dutch and French coppyes. By G.P. 1584.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1584</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01592</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11720</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119710</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854917</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854917</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20375</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01592)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20375)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 568:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Newes out of Germanie. A most wonderfull and true discouse of a cruell murderer, who had kylled in his life tyme, nine hundred, threescore and odde persons among which six of them were his owne children begotten on a young woman which he forceablie kept in a caue seuen yeeres, with the manner how he was taken, and the aboundaunce of wealth that was found in the said caue: executed at Berkessell on the 14. of Iune. Translated and published according to the Dutch and French coppyes. By G.P. 1584.</title>
                  <author>Pen, George.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By J. Wolfe] for George Pen, dwelling at Ipswich,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted [at London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1584]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication, printer's name and date of publication from STC.</note>
                  <note>G.P. = George Pen--Cf. STC.</note>
                  <note>Concerning the life, capture and execution of Christeman Gempertinga.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; some pages show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gempertinga, Christeman, d. 1584.</term>
               <term>Crime --  Germany --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Criminals --  Germany --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20375:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 41 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:20375:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 41 -->
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Newes out of <hi>Germaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A moſt wonderfull and true <hi>diſcourſe of a cruell murderer,</hi> who had kylled in his life tyme, nine <hi>hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, threeſcore and odde perſons among which</hi> ſix of them were his owne children, begotten <hi>on a young woman which he forceablie kept in a</hi> Caue ſeuen yeeres, with the manner how he was taken, and the aboundaunce of wealth that was found in the ſaid Caue: executed at Berkeſſell on the 14. of Iune.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated and publiſhed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> to the Dutch and <hi>French Coppyes. By G.P.</hi> 1584.</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               <hi>Imprinted for George Pen,</hi> dwelling at Ipſwich.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:20375:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 42 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:20375:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 42 -->
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>A Letter written to a</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perſonage of the Cittie of Mentz, <hi>by a Gentleman of credit, who ſawe</hi> this murderer executed.</head>
            <p>RIght honourable and my eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all good freend, I haue not at this time any newes wherewith to acquiant you, but only this ſtraunge and admirable occaſion which lately happened: the truth whereof I truſt my credit is ſufficient with your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to confirme, and the rather, for that I not only heard the murderers examination, but was alſo an eye wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his death. And albeit it may ſeeme incredible, yet thus much I can aſſure you, that I ſaw the ſcrole which was found in the murtherers Caue, wherin he had written the names of al one that he had murdred, and I heard him alſo affirme it with his owne mouth. The diſcourſe thereof follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, which I commit to your iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſo I commend your honor to the heauenly protection.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:20375:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 43 -->
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A rare and <hi>straunge Diſcourſe, of a</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious and cruell <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer, named</hi> Chriſteman Gempertin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga, who leading a bloody life of longe <hi>time, and beeing at laſt apprehended therefore</hi> confeſſed that in his life time he had ſlaine nine hundred, three ſcore and foure perſons, and enten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to murder ſtill, till he had made vp the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of a thouſand. For which horrible murders, hee was executed in the Towne of Berkeſſell, neere to the Cittie of Mentz in Germanie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the Forreſt of <hi>Fraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg,</hi> within a league of <hi>Berkeſſell,</hi> there liued for the ſpace of 13. yeeres one <hi>Chriſteman Gem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinga</hi> of <hi>Corpen,</hi> two leagues diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce from <hi>Collen,</hi> whoſe only maintenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce was by robbing and ſpoyling of the paſſingers, and ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:20375:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 43 -->
a fit and commodious place for his purpoſe he had prouided himſelfe of, as he might at pleaſure diſcerne them that traueiled on the hye wayes, either to <hi>Mentz, Dietenhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, Treuers,</hi> or <hi>Duche de Luxen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg,</hi> to which places Merchaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes did ordinarily traffique, becauſe they were Townes of great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie for their affaires. And as they trauailed thorow this Forreſt, he and his companions would ſet vppon them, and hauing robbed them of their goods and treaſure, would likewiſe diſpoyle them of their liues, and afterward cauſe them to bee throwen into a deepe pit in the Forreſt, which he had or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained for the purpoſe: as for theyr apparell, weapons and ſuch like, he caryed to his Caue, which in time was ſo well ſtored with Harque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes, Swordes, Murrians, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſans and Corſſetes, that a great ſtrength could not haue ouer come
<pb facs="tcp:20375:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 44 -->
him and his companyons.</p>
            <p>And for the goods, which he tooke from the Merchauntes and paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, his Caue was ſo well furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed there with, beeing of all ſorts of Merchandiſe, and wares belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Allemaignes</hi> and other Nations: as the quantitie thereof was iudged ſufficient to furniſh a Fayre and the value thereof eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med more worth, then 70000. Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rins of gold of <hi>Allemaigne.</hi> And beſides, there was founde in his Caue alſo when he was taken, ſo great ſtore of wine, bread, fleſh, rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, &amp; figs, as would haue ſuffiſed him for one whole yeere. Amongſt all the paſſengers that traueiled thorowe this Forreſt, it chaunced one day, that a proper woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert</hi> neere y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Rhine</hi> A Coopers daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter went to ſee her brethren &amp; had oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to paſſe that way, this villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous murderer hauing eſpyed her, made haſt to her, and hauing diſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led her of ſuch thinges as ſhe had
<pb facs="tcp:20375:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 44 -->
about her, intended to murder her, as he had doon all the other: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ouercome with the ſight of her fayre face and body, helde hys handes, and intreated her to keepe him co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany there in that place, and be contended with that kinde of life which he vſed, otherwiſe he would likewiſe kil her. The woman feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of death, and ſeeing the horrible maſſacre of dead bodyes in the pit before her, whom ſhe ſhould keepe company if ſhe denyed his requeſt: conſented vnto him, and promiſed neuer to betray or reueale him to any, whereby his life might ſtand in any hazard. On this condition he lead her with him into his Caue and there ſhe liued with him for the ſpace of 7. yeeres, in which time ſhe had 6. Children by him, which ſo ſoone as they were borne, hee would take them and breake theyr neckes and pull them by the feete and head to ſtreatch them in length and afterward would goe hange
<pb facs="tcp:20375:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 45 -->
them vp on a high place that he had prouided for the nonce: and then he would ſtand looking on them, and ſeeing the winde to make them waue vp and downe, this merciles villaine would ſay: <hi>Daunce daunce my loouing Children, for Gempertin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga your Father dooth ſounde you a daunce.</hi> It was a meruailous greefe and great hart breaking to the poore woman, to ſee her tender In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantes vſed ſo deſpitefully by theyr owne Father, and gladly ſhe would haue beene rid of that kinde of lyfe, but that ſhe could not get thence by any meanes: for hee had tyed her with a chaine, and ſhe could goe no furder then the Chaine gaue her li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, which pollicie he vſed, leaſt ſhe ſhould eſcape away while hee and his companions were abroad, and ſo his dealings might be diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered. After that he had robbed and killed for a long ſeaſon, he grewe doubtfull of his companions, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery day did more and more miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt
<pb facs="tcp:20375:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 45 -->
them: ſo that at length he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed a meane to eaſe his doubt, and one day making merry amongſt them, he conuayed in theyr meate and drinke ſuch a violent and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame kinde of poyſon, as they all dyed thereof within 5. or ſix houres after: which he perceiuing, threwe them into the pit to the other bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes that they had murdered.</p>
            <p>When he was thus rid of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, and had no body left with him but the woman, he wexed ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what doubtful of her lykewiſe: but God willing to reueale the horrible villainies of this murderer, cauſed the woman to be verie importunat in requeſt to him, that ſhe might go ſee her freends, and wrought alſo in his minde ſo accordingly, that hee gaue her leaue to goe, aſſuring him ſelfe on her promiſe, that ſhe would neuer reueale him. She went and ſawe her Parents, and returned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine without vttering any worde of him, which made him the more
<pb facs="tcp:20375:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 46 -->
willing to ſuffer her to go againe, and entring the ſtreetes of <hi>Berkeſſel,</hi> ſhe ſawe little children playing, the ſight wherof, and the remembrance how villainouſly her owne children were murdred, cauſed her to fal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to extreeme complaintes and paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, at laſt ſhe brake foorth into theſe dolorous ſpeeches. <hi>O God which dooſt maintaine all thinges, and from whome the death of my children cannot be hidden, &amp; who knoweſt the promiſe I haue made by conſtraint: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde me in mercie, and pittie the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhes I haue endured in my fleſhe and blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe her complaintes were ſo pittiful both in ſhew &amp; hearing, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many gathered about her to know the cauſe of her lamentations, and very earneſt they were with her to vnderſtand the cauſe of her paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate afflictions: but they could by no meanes preuaile in theyr inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, for that ſhe ſayde, ſhe had proteſted ſecrecie of her greefes by ſolempne
<pb facs="tcp:20375:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 46 -->
oath, and ſhe would not vtter them to any. Some of them that ſtoode by &amp; heard her wordes, infourmed the Iuſtices in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Towne of the matter, whervpon ſhe was brought before them, and there ſhe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued in the ſame obſtinate opinion ſhe dyd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: neuertheleſſe, they labored ſtyl with her, &amp; gaue her to vnderſtand, that a wilful oath might endam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage her ſoule, and by reuealing it, ſhe might e<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cape many daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous threatninges for the contrary. By which perſwaſions ſhe anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her ſelf, and from the beginning to the end ſhe diſcourſed the whole circumſtaunce by particulers, of the murderer and his lyuing: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vppon, the Iuſtices concluded with her, what courſe ſhe ſhould take to preuayle in this matter, both to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray the murderer, and ſaue her ſelf blameleſſe. Not long after they put in readines thyrtie wel appointed Soldiours, who ſhould folow the woman a farre off tyl they fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the
<pb facs="tcp:20375:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 47 -->
Caue: and ſhee (according to the Iuſtices direction (tooke with her a bagge of Peaſe, which ſhe ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered along the way as ſhe went, by which meanes the Soldiours could not miſſe of the right way to the Caue. When ſhe came to the Caue, the murderer was very glad of her returne, and ieſting familiar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with her, at laſt he layde him downe on the ground, and laide his head in her lappe, where by her rubbing and ſoft ſcratching it, he fel a ſleepe. Within a whyle after, the Soldiors came to the Caue, and finding him thus ſleeping, they laid handes on him, and bound him ſo, that he could not reſiſt them: which hee perceyuing, cried out, <hi>O thou diſloyall whore, it is long ſince I miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted this thy trechery, &amp; I thought to haue ſped thee with the reſt of thy fellowes.</hi> The Soldiours brought him with them to <hi>Berkeſſel,</hi> where being put to the torment, he confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb facs="tcp:20375:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 47 -->
all his former villainies, &amp; that he had murdered 964. perſons, and howe he intended to continew in murdering ſtyl, tyl he had ſlaine ſo many as came to a thouſand, &amp; then he would murder no more: and to verifie his wordes, the Soldiours preſented the Iuſtices a ſcrowle, wherein the names were written by his owne hand, of all them that he had murdered, and on what ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral dayes he murdered them. Heer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon he was condemned, and had his legges and armes, and bones broken with an yron inſtrument fit for the purpoſe, and afterward was laide on a Cart wheele without the Towne (as it is the maner in other Countries) where he liued for the ſpace of nine daies after, being dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuſtained with drinke and meat, to maintayne his lyfe in ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame paine: and all the goodes that were found in his Caue, were brought to the Towne, and they
<pb facs="tcp:20375:8"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 48 -->
and the woman kept in holde, the Magiſtrates being not as yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued how to deale with them. It is thought, that had not the Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors found him ſo ſleeping, they could hardly haue taken him, he had ſo many Caliuers, Harguebuſes, and Dags ready charged in his Caue, &amp; was of himſelfe ſuch a ſtoute, ſtrong and actiue man, &amp; the place where he was, did ſerue him in all reſpects able to reſiſt a great number.</p>
            <p>The conſideration of this ſtraunge and monſtrous diſcourſe, I committee to your honours good conſtruction, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting it a parte of my duety, to make your honour acquainted with any notable thing I can heare of: And ſo I humbly take my leaue.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:20375:8"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 48 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
